→ 通往ISS的旅途
第一部分：联盟火箭发射
拜科努尔航天发射场位于哈萨克斯坦荒无人烟的大草原中央
The Baikonour Cosmodrome located in the middle of the deserted steppes of Kazakhstan
字幕翻译/压制：NeXT-X6，旋火
视频来源：youtu.be/AVvgpKt5uCA
原视频发布日期：20130808
原作者名：European Space Agency, ESA
是用于前往国际空间站的俄罗斯航天发射设施
is the Russian space launch facility used to start the journey towards the International Space Station.
这是一个巨大的综合设施 包含几个技术大楼：
It is a huge complex that comprises several technical buildings:
一些用于组装和准备火箭
some for assembling and preparing the rockets
其他的建筑为技术人员 工程师 和宇航员提供住宿
and others to accommodate the technicians, engineers, and the crews.
50多年之前 尤里·加加林就是从拜科努尔开始他环绕地球的非凡之旅
It was from Baikonur that Yuri Gagarin began his extraordinary journey around the Earth more than 50 years ago.
现在 联盟号飞船每次发射会将三个新宇航员带上国际空间站
Today every launch of the Soyuz vehicle brings three new crew members onboard the International Space Station.
他们在星城准备任务 星城是莫斯科附近的宇航员培训中心
They prepare for their mission in Star City the training centre of the cosmonauts located near Moscow.
在踏上发射台之前
Before stepping onto the launch pad,
所有的宇航员都必须经过数百小时的理论和实践培训
all the crew members have to undergo hundreds of training hours both theoretical and practical
才能在任何情况下操作和控制的联盟号飞船
to be able to operate and control the Soyuz spacecraft in any situation.
实践培训使用逼真的飞船模型
The practical part of the training makes use of realistic models of the spacecraft
模型能使宇航员体验几乎真实的处境
that allow the cosmonauts to feel almost as if they were in a real situation.
他们都跟随许多其他从拜科努尔起飞的宇航员的道路
They all follow the path of many others who flew before them from Baikonour.
让我们看看联盟号火箭是如何工作的
Let's discover how a Soyuz rocket works.
该火箭总长度大约是50米
The rocket has a total length of approximately 50 m
直径最大处10米
and a diameter of up to 10 m.
总质量约310吨
The total mass is about 310 tons.
它由3个部分组成 这些叫做火箭的分级
It consists of 3 parts called stages.
它使用煤油和液氧的混合物 以产生所需的推进力
A mixture of kerosene and liquid oxygen is used in order to generate the required propulsion.
联盟号飞船矗立在火箭的顶部
On top of the rocket stands the Soyuz spacecraft itself,
包裹在火箭的鼻锥内
encapsulated within the structure of the rocket's nose.
在发射台上 四个绿色的机械臂确保火箭在升空前处于正确的位置
On the launch pad, four green arms ensure that the rocket is positioned properly before lift-off.
这些机械臂会旋转 在火箭离开地面时释放它
The arms will mechanically rotate away to release the rocket while it leaves the ground。
训练成功完成
The training being successfully completed.
宇航员都准备好发射了
the crew members are ready for the launch.
而火箭矗立在发射台上
And the rocket stands on the launch pad.
起飞前两个半小时 宇航员进入飞船
Two and a half hours before lift-off, the crew finally enter the spacecraft.
并配合地面控制人员 开始准备发射
And start preparing it for the launch in collaboration with the ground controllers.
他们现在准备好发射了
They are now set for the launch.
现在宇航员坐在300吨推进剂的顶部
The cosmonauts are now sitting on top of 300 tons of propellant.
如果出现问题 会发生什么？
What happens if anything goes wrong?
联盟号火箭配备了一个强大健壮的系统
The Soyuz rocket is equipped with a robust and powerful system
用于在发射台上的火箭开始燃烧或爆炸时拯救宇航员
designed to save the crew in case the rocket were to start burning or explode on the launch pad.
这就是逃逸塔
This is the launch escape tower.
逃逸塔本身就是一个小而强大的火箭
The launch escape tower is itself a small yet powerful rocket
由使几个使用固体推进剂的引擎组成
made up of several engines which use solid propellant.
在对宇航员有紧迫威胁的情况下 例如爆炸
It is capable of quickly extracting the crew compartments from the rest of the rocket
它能够迅速地拉出载人舱 远离余下的火箭部分
in case of an imminent threat to the crew like an explosion for instance.
该机制可自动触发
The mechanism may be triggered automatically
或根据地面控制命令触发
or upon command from the ground controllers.
在俄罗斯航天史上 （逃逸塔）这个逃生系统唯有一次被投入使用
On only one occasion in the history of Russian cosmonautics was this escape system put to use.
1983年9月 火箭正准备发射两位苏联宇航员到礼炮7号空间站
In September 1983, while the rocket was ready to lift-off to bring two Soviet cosmonauts to the Salyut 7 station,
点火前90秒 一个阀门无法关闭 导致煤油溅到发射台上并点燃
a valve failed to close just 90 seconds before final ignition causing kerosene to spill onto the pad and ignite.
幸运的是 地面很快就意识到 宇航员受到威胁
Fortunately, it was quickly realized that the crew was endangered
于是地面控制人员激活逃生系统
and the ground controllers activated the escape system.
爆炸螺栓引爆 使载人舱从飞船的其余部分分离
Explosive bolts fired to separate the crew compartments from the rest of the spacecraft
和逃生引擎发动 拖着载人舱离开推进器
and the escape motor fired, dragging the crew compartments free of the boosters.
虽然两位航天员经历了5秒14至17g的加速度
Although the two crew members experienced an acceleration of 14 to 17 g for 5 seconds,
他们在载人舱中安全降落在距发射台约4公里的地方
they landed safely onboard their capsule some 4 kilometres away from the launch pad.
g负荷是表达加速度的常用方法
The g-load is a common way to express the acceleration
换句话说是宇航员在速度变化时可以感觉到的力
or in other words the force that the crew may feel during changes in velocity.
这两个宇航员Strekalov和Titov将在之后执行几个非常成功的任务
The two cosmonauts Strekalov and Titov would go on to fly several highly successful missions in later years.
这一事件证明了发射逃逸系统有多么可靠
This incident proved how reliable the launch escape system really is.
现在让我们看看发射程序
Let's go through the launch sequence now.
在倒计时为0时 火箭起飞
At T-0 We have lift-off.
全部推力由4个侧助推器和火箭的芯级提供
Full thrust is provided by the 4 side boosters and the central block of the rocket.
芯级点火 同时4个助推器提供额外的推力
The core block is ignited at the same time as the 4 boosters to provide an additional thrust.
然后火箭开始执行俯仰机动
The rocket then initiates a manoeuvre called the pitch maneuver
得到朝向预定轨道的正确方向
to get the proper orientation towards the desired orbit.
在宇航员身上的加速度开始慢慢增加至1.5g
The acceleration on the crew members starts to slowly increase to 1.5 g.
45秒后 火箭已经达到11km的高度和1,640km/h的速度
45 seconds later, the rocket has already reached an altitude of 11 km and a velocity of 1,640 km/h.
这时火箭结构必须承受最大的压力(最大动压)
This is the moment the rocket must withstand the maximum pressure on its structure.
宇航员会感受到两倍于地面上的正常体重
The cosmonauts feel twice their normal weight on the ground.
看着地面上的轨迹投影 我们可以观察到 火箭已经跨越16公里
Looking at the projection of the track on the ground, we can observe that the rocket has already crossed 16 km.
快进
飞行接近两分钟后
After almost two minutes into the flight,
火箭位于超过40公里的高度
the rocket is at an altitude of more than 40 km,
高到足以丢弃发射逃逸塔
high enough to get rid of the launch escape tower.
几秒钟后 四个捆绑式助推器停止工作
A few seconds later, the four strap-on boosters stop firing,
它们已经消耗了所有的推进剂
having consumed all the propellant they contained.
现在没用的它们被抛弃 离开芯级
Being of no use now they are jettisoned from the main core
而芯级将继续工作 现在被称为第二级
which continues to fire and is now called the second stage.
为防止严重故障的情况 航天器仍然可以从火箭的其余部分分离
In case of a severe malfunction at this point, the spacecraft can still separate from the rest of the rocket
并安全返回到地面 无需额外的推力
and come back safely to the ground without the need for additional propulsion.
碎片沿着弹道坠落在一个无人居住的区域
The debris follow a trajectory that leads it to hit the ground in an uninhabited area
距离发射台350公里以上
located more than 350 km from the launch pad
不久 宇航员身上将经历最大的加速度 3.5倍于自身的重量
Soon the crew members will experience the maximum acceleration on their bodies, 3.5 times their own weight.
但是这只有几秒钟
But only for a few seconds.
这是宇航员最耗费体力的时刻
This is the most physically demanding moment for the cosmonauts.
在此期间 第二级继续工作3分钟
In the meantime, the second stage continues to fire for 3 more minutes.
然后保护航天器的结构被抛离
The structure that protects the spacecraft is then jettisoned.
再一次 碎片沿着安全的弹道坠落在距离发射场530公里的地面
Once again, the debris will follow a safe trajectory to hit the ground 530 km away from the launch site.
飞船现在完全暴露在宇宙空间
The spacecraft is now fully exposed to space.
现在来自外部的光线可以通过小窗口进入载人舱
The light from outside can now enter the crew compartment through the small windows.
现在距离起飞已经约5分钟了
It's now been approximately 5 minutes since lift-off.
慢动作
Two seconds before the extinction of the second stage the third stage is ignited.
第二级关闭前两秒钟第三级被点燃
慢动作
然后第二级从火箭的剩余部分分开
Then the second stage separates from the rest of the rocket.
第三级引擎
将在接下来的4分钟继续工作
The engine of the third stage will continue firing for the next 4 minutes.
同之前4个助推器一样
第二级沿着安全的弹道落回地球
As with the 4 boosters, the second stage follows a safe trajectory down to Earth.
火箭已经在170km的高度
并以13250km/h的速度飞行
The rocket is already at an altitude of 170 km, and travelling at a velocity of 13,250 km/h.
然后连接第三级与第二级的环形段(级间段)被抛弃
Then the circular section that links the second stage with the third stage is jettisoned
同时火箭继续向距地表约220km的目标轨道进发
while the rocket goes on to reach the targeted orbit around 220 km above the surface of the Earth.
一旦进入预定轨道 大约是发射后9分钟 最后一个引擎关闭
Once on the desired orbit, approximately 9 minutes into the launch, the last engine is cut-off.
飞船最终从火箭分离
The spacecraft finally separates from the rocket.
宇航员现在可以感受到微重力
The cosmonauts can now feel the microgravity.
片刻之后 天线和太阳能电池阵列被部署
Moments later, the antennas and the solar arrays are deployed.
飞船现在处于前往国际空间站的途中
The spacecraft is now on its way to the International Space Station.